<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Integrative Dashboard - OpenAlex Feed</title>
    <link>https://digitalgeosciences.github.io/dashboard3.2/</link>
    <description>Recent publications with OpenAlex abstracts and topics.</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 21:11:23 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <ttl>60</ttl>
    <item>
      <title>Contact morphology of sand particles in dunes</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-025-15888-8</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4413307018</guid>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Alonso-Marroquin, Sarmad Zafar Khan, Abdullah Alqubalee, Péter Móra, Abdullatif Al‐Shuhail</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Scientific Reports</dc:publisher>
      <category>Morphology (biology)</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Paleontology</category>
      <description>Abstract: This study presents an analysis of the morphology of sand particles and their contacts using high-resolution microcomputer tomography (CT) and scanning electron microscopy (SEM). Raw 3D images are filtered, binarized, and smoothed to distinguish the granular space from the void space. The 3D granular space is segmented via an advanced adaptive watershed algorithm. The grain segmentation is used for contact detection and contact network extraction. The topography of each grain is diverse, fascinating, and shaped by a landscape of ridges and basins. This topography is reflected in the way the grains come into contact. Unlike the common conception of point contacts, we observe contacts over large surface areas, concave-like contacts due to ridge-basin interactions, and doughnut-like contacts due to incomplete contact between high ridges and deep basins. Although most of the interactions are due to a single contact, a significant number of multiple contact interactions are observed. SEM images show two key features: First, the sand surfaces are not quartz-clean but are coated with clay particles. Second, the basins are not empty but are partially filled with silt particles that are cemented with clay. This is a comprehensive experimental investigation to determine the basis for advanced contact models of the micromechanical investigation of the strength of sand aggregates and wave propagation herein. The proposed micro- and nanocharacterization of contact morphologies paves the w…&#10;Topics: Morphology (biology), Geology, Paleontology&#10;Venue: Scientific Reports&#10;Year: 2025&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact morphology of sand particles in dunes</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-6244542/v1</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4409556117</guid>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Alonso Marroquin, Sarmad Zafar Khan, Abdullah Alqubalee, Péter Móra, Abdullatif Al‐Shuhail</dc:creator>
      <category>Morphology (biology)</category>
      <category>Sand dune stabilization</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Geomorphology</category>
      <category>Paleontology</category>
      <description>Abstract: &lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt; This study presents an analysis of the morphology of sand particles and their contacts using high-resolution microcomputer tomography (CT) and scanning electron microscopy (SEM). Raw 3D images are filtered, binarized, and smoothed to distinguish the granular space from the void space. The 3D granular space is segmented via an advanced adaptive watershed algorithm. The grain segmentation is used for contact detection and contact network extraction. The topography of each grain is diverse, fascinating, and shaped by a landscape of ridges and basins. This topography is reflected in the way the grains come into contact. Unlike the common conception of point contacts, we observe contacts over large surface areas, concave-like contacts due to ridge-basin interactions, and doughnut-like contacts due to incomplete contact between high ridges and deep basins. Although most of the interactions are due to a single contact, a significant number of multiple contact interactions are observed. SEM images show two key features: First, the sand surfaces are not quartz-clean but are coated with clay particles. Second, the basins are not empty but are partially filled with silt particles that are cemented with clay. This is a comprehensive experimental investigation to determine the basis for advanced contact models of the micromechanical investigation of the strength of sand aggregates and wave propagation herein. The proposed micro- and nanocharacterization of contact …&#10;Topics: Morphology (biology), Sand dune stabilization, Geology, Geomorphology, Paleontology&#10;Year: 2025&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>513Chapter 19 Various elements of a potential hydrogen system in Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1515/9783111437040-019</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4412890921</guid>
      <dc:creator>Manzar Fawad, Scott Whattam, Abdullah Alqubalee, Ahmed Al‐Yaseri</dc:creator>
      <category>Ancient history</category>
      <category>History</category>
      <description>Topics: Ancient history, History&#10;Year: 2025&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagenetic controls on the quality of shallow marine sandstones: An example from the Cambro-Ordovician Saq Formation, central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jafrearsci.2024.105295</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4399072009</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdulwahab Muhammad Bello, Anas Muhammad Salisu, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abduljamiu O. Amao, Murtada Al-Hashem, Abdulkarim Al-Hussaini, Khalid Al–Ramadan</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Journal of African Earth Sciences</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <category>Ordovician</category>
      <category>Petrology</category>
      <category>Paleontology</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Diagenesis, Ordovician, Petrology, Paleontology&#10;Venue: Journal of African Earth Sciences&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 9</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shift from arc to within-plate magmatism at 635 Ma as recorded by Neoproterozoic dikes, southern Midyan terrane, NW Arabian Shield</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.precamres.2024.107430</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4398159676</guid>
      <dc:creator>Scott Whattam, Robert J. Stern, Hossein Azizi, Keewook Yi, Haitham M. Baggazi, Abdullah Alqubalee, Fatemeh Nouri, Brian R. Jicha, Yanick Brice Lemdjou, Abdelhamid El Fakharani</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Precambrian Research</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Terrane</category>
      <category>Magmatism</category>
      <category>Dike</category>
      <category>Shield</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Terrane, Magmatism, Dike, Shield&#10;Venue: Precambrian Research&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 6</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking the H2 potential in Saudi Arabia: Exploring serpentinites as a source for H2 production</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-egu24-5447</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4392600402</guid>
      <dc:creator>Kebba Saidy, Manzar Fawad, Scott Whattam, Abdullatif Al‐Shuhail, Abdullah A. Alshuhail, Abdullah Alqubalee, Farooqui Mohammed, Faris Sulistyohariyanto, Sabyasachi Chattopadhyay</dc:creator>
      <category>Production (economics)</category>
      <category>Business</category>
      <category>Economics</category>
      <category>Macroeconomics</category>
      <description>Abstract: The global transition to a low-carbon energy future has ignited interest in hydrogen as a clean and versatile energy carrier. Saudi Arabia contains, vast tracts of mantle-dominated Neoproterozoic ophiolites overlain by a sedimentary cover in the east. Our research explores the untapped potential of Saudi Arabia&amp;amp;#8217;s ophiolite serpentinites as a possible source of hydrogen generation through serpentinization and related processes. H2 is derived from serpentinization, which primarily involves the hydration of minerals rich in iron and magnesium, (e.g., olivine), resulting in the formation of serpentine and H2. &amp;amp;#160;We have conducted a comprehensive assessment of serpentinites in the Arabian Shield employing the Geographic Information System (GIS) to locate, Arabian ophiolites with the largest ultramafic segments. Ophiolites studied include Jabal Ess, Jabal Wask, Bi&amp;amp;#8217;r Tululah, and Jabal Tharwah. Subsequent to ophiolite identification, we delineated fractures and measured fracture density to provide insight into the potential of serpentinite fractures on the amount of hydrogen seepage and the rate of hydrogen production. The results of our quantitative fracture density analysis and their relation to the volume and rate of hydrogen production will be discussed. A complimentary H2 anomaly survey will ground-truth the results of this study.&#10;Topics: Production (economics), Business, Economics, Macroeconomics&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Source rock potential, thermal maturity, and depositional environment of the Ordovician Ra’an Shale Member, central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaesx.2024.100174</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4391286506</guid>
      <dc:creator>Faisal AlGhamdi, Lamidi Babalola, Abdullah Alqubalee, Israa S. Abu‐Mahfouz, Bandar Alotaibi, Mohammed Abouelresh</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Journal of Asian Earth Sciences X</dc:publisher>
      <category>Siltstone</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Sedimentary depositional environment</category>
      <category>Petrography</category>
      <category>Oil shale</category>
      <description>Abstract: The Ordovician Ra’an Shale Member of the Qassim Formation in Saudi Arabia has potential as an unconventional hydrocarbon play. This shale unit, however, has not been studied in detail for its geochemical characteristics, thermal maturity, and reservoir quality. This study aims to investigate this shale member from a well-exposed section at Khashm Ra’an in the Qassim region, central Saudi Arabia. Detailed fieldwork followed by comprehensive geochemical and petrographic analyses were conducted to evaluate the hydrocarbon potential and interpret the depositional setting of this shale member. Integration of field sedimentological description, sample description and thin section petrography facilitated the identification of partially burrowed laminated fish-bearing shale, bioturbated siltstone, graptolite-bearing shale, shale/siltstone and sandstone/shale interbeds in the investigated outcrop. The intervals were sandwiched between the bioturbated sandstone of the underlying Kahfah Sandstone and the overlying Quwarah Formation. These lithofacies are interpreted to have been deposited in a shallow marine depositional setting. The preservation of graptolite in some intervals indicates low bottom dissolved oxygen conditions. The mineralogical analysis indicated that clay minerals, quartz, and feldspars are the major mineralogical components in the study samples. Based on mineralogical compositions, the studied samples were classified into three main lithofacies types; silica-rich argi…&#10;Topics: Siltstone, Geology, Sedimentary depositional environment, Petrography, Oil shale&#10;Venue: Journal of Asian Earth Sciences X&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 3</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mineralogy and Geochemistry of the Paleocene–Eocene Palana Formation in Western Rajasthan, India: Insights for Sedimentary Paleoenvironmental Conditions and Volcanic Activity</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.3390/min14020126</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4391167607</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Hail Hakimi, Alok Kumar, Abdullah Alqubalee, Alok K. Singh, Mohammed Almobarky, Afikah Rahim, Mohammad Alqudah, Aref Lashin, Khairul Azlan Mustapha, Waqas Naseem</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Minerals</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Organic matter</category>
      <category>Geochemistry</category>
      <category>Total organic carbon</category>
      <category>Anoxic waters</category>
      <description>Abstract: Organic-rich shale rocks from the Paleocene–Eocene Palana Formation in western Rajasthan, India, were systematically investigated based on inorganic and organic geochemistry combined with microscopic examinations to evaluate the sedimentary paleoenvironmental conditions and volcanic activity and their impact on the high organic carbon accumulation. The Palana shales are categorized by high organic matter (OM) and sulfur contents, with total values up to 36.23 wt.% and 2.24 wt.%, respectively. The richness of phytoplankton algae (i.e., telalginite and lamalginite) together with redox-sensitive trace elements further suggests a marine setting and anoxic environmental conditions during the Paleocene–Eocene. The significant low oxygen conditions may contribute to enhancing the preservation of organic matter during deposition. The mineralogical and inorganic geochemical indicators demonstrate that the Palana organic-rich shale facies was accumulated in a warm and humid climate with moderate salinity stratification conditions in the water columns, thereby contributing to the high bioproductivity of the phytoplankton algae blooms within the photic zone. The presence of significant contents of zeolite derived from volcanic material together with silica minerals such as apophyllite and tridymite in most of the Palana organic-rich shales indicates a volcanic origin and supports hydrothermal activities during the Paleocene–Eocene period. These volcanic activities in this case are consid…&#10;Topics: Geology, Organic matter, Geochemistry, Total organic carbon, Anoxic waters&#10;Venue: Minerals&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 5</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controls on mechanical properties of a carbonate mudstone: Insights from non-destructive techniques and geochemical data</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2024.106702</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4390685983</guid>
      <dc:creator>Baqer Albensaad, Septriandi A. Chan, John Humphrey, Abdullah Alqubalee, Ammar El‐Husseiny, Yaser Alzayer</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Porosity</category>
      <category>Terrigenous sediment</category>
      <category>Mineralogy</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <description>Abstract: This study quantifies geomechanical properties of carbonate mudrocks in the Arabian intra-shelf basin, focusing on different sedimentologic zones (proximal to distal). Core-based mechanical properties were obtained through unconfined conditions. Micro Rebound Testing (MRT) was conducted on 700′ ft of core at 0.5 ft intervals to capture high-resolution rock hardness (HLD), unconfined compressive strength (UCS), and static Young&apos;s Modulus (E). Additional tests validated log-based parameters, including impulse hammer, acoustic velocity testing for (E), P-wave and S-wave velocities (Vp and Vs), scratch testing, and XRF/XRD analyses for mineralogical and elemental variability impact on mechanical properties. Multivariate statistical analysis correlates mechanical properties with elemental data, showing direct proportionality to calcium percentage, (E), Vp, and Vs, while inversely correlated to aluminum, iron, sulfur, and total organic carbon (TOC), especially in distal zones. Porosity, as measured by neutron porosity log, is a significant control on mechanical properties, with higher porosity resulting in lower mechanical properties at any given calcium percentage. Variations in geomechanical properties within each zone are principally controlled by depositional environments, sediment supply, diagenesis, and a pycnocline dividing the water column into anoxic, dysoxic (or suboxic), and oxic conditions. Zone 1A and 4 exhibit high brittleness characterized by high Ca-calcite, HLD, (E…&#10;Topics: Geology, Porosity, Terrigenous sediment, Mineralogy, Diagenesis&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 4</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagenetic Controls on Reservoir Porosity of Aeolian and Fluvial Deposits: A Case Study from Permo-Carboniferous Sandstones of Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13369-023-08590-2</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4390510283</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdulwahab Muhammad Bello, Abduljamiu O. Amao, Abdullah Alqubalee, Murtada Al-Hashem, Houssin Albarri, Mohammed Al‐Masrahy, Khalid Al‐Ramadan, Lamidi Babalola</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Illite</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <category>Cementation (geology)</category>
      <category>Authigenic</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Illite, Diagenesis, Cementation (geology), Authigenic&#10;Venue: Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 6</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genesis of Grain-Coating Clays and Their Effect on the Development of Feldspar Overgrowths: A Case Study of the Late Cambrian to Early Ordovician Barik Formation Sandstone Reservoir, Haushi-Huqf Region, Central Oman</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-48758-3_8</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4392964788</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed A. K. El‐Ghali, İftikhar Ahmed Abbasi, Olga Shelukhina, Mohamed S. H. Moustafa, Arshad Ali, Osman Salad Hersi, Shahad Al Mahrooqi, Khalid Al–Ramadan, Abdulwahab Muhammad Bello, Hezam Al-Awah, Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Advances in Science, Technology &amp; Innovation/Advances in science, technology &amp; innovation</dc:publisher>
      <category>Ordovician</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Feldspar</category>
      <category>Geochemistry</category>
      <category>Petrology</category>
      <description>Topics: Ordovician, Geology, Feldspar, Geochemistry, Petrology&#10;Venue: Advances in Science, Technology &amp; Innovation/Advances in science, technology &amp; innovation&#10;Year: 2024&#10;Citations: 3</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mineralogy and Geochemistry of the Paleocene-Eocene Palana Formation in Western Rajasthan, India: Insights for Sedimentary Paleoenvironmental Conations and Volcanic Activity</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202311.1550.v1</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4388960641</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Hail Hakimi, Alok Kumar, Abdullah Alqubalee, Alok K. Singh, Mohammed Almobarky, Afikah Rahim, Mohammad Alqudah, Aref Lashin, Khairul Azlan Mustapha, Waqas Naseem</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Preprints.org</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Anoxic waters</category>
      <category>Photic zone</category>
      <category>Organic matter</category>
      <category>Geochemistry</category>
      <description>Abstract: Organic-rich shale deposits of the Paleocene-Eocene Palana Formation in western Rajasthan, India were systematically analyzed based on the elemental composition and organic geochemistry combined with microscopic examinations to evaluate the sedimentary paleoenvironmental conations and volcanic activity and their impact on the high organic carbon accumulation. The Palana shales are categorized by high OM and sulfur contents with total values up to 36.23 wt. % and 2.24 wt. %, respectively, suggesting marine setting and anoxic environmental conditions during the Paleocene-Eocene period. The richness of phytoplankton algae (i.e., telalginite and lamalginite) together with redox-sensitive trace elements further suggests anoxic environmental conditions. The significant low oxygen conditions may contributes to enhance preservation of organic matter during deposition. The mineralogical and inorganic geochemical indicators demonstrate that the Palana organic-rich shale facies was accumulated in warm and humid climate and low salinity stratification conditions of the water columns, thereby contributing to high bioproductivity of the phytoplankton algae blooms within the photic zone. The presence of the high concentrations of Fe-rich silica minerals such as olivine in most of the Palana organic-rich shales facility volcanic origin and supports hydrothermal activities during the Paleocene-Eocene period. These volcanic activities in this case are considered influx of large masses of nutri…&#10;Topics: Geology, Anoxic waters, Photic zone, Organic matter, Geochemistry&#10;Venue: Preprints.org&#10;Year: 2023&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depositional and sequence stratigraphic controls on diagenesis in the Upper Cambrian-Lower Ordovician Barik Formation, central Oman: Implications for prediction of reservoir porosity in a hybrid-energy delta system</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2023.106611</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4388923668</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed A. K. El‐Ghali, Olga Shelukhina, İftikhar Ahmed Abbasi, Mohamed S. H. Moustafa, Osman Salad Hersi, Numair Ahmed Siddiqui, Khalid Al–Ramadan, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abdulwahab Muhammad Bello, Abduljamiu O. Amao</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <category>Arenite</category>
      <category>Cementation (geology)</category>
      <category>Sedimentary depositional environment</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Diagenesis, Arenite, Cementation (geology), Sedimentary depositional environment&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2023&#10;Citations: 27</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characteristics, distribution, and origin of ferruginous deposits within the Late Ordovician glaciogenic setting of Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-45563-9</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4387996609</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, Anas Muhammad Salisu, Abdulwahab Muhammad Bello, Abdulkarim Al-Hussaini, Khalid Al–Ramadan</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Scientific Reports</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Sedimentary depositional environment</category>
      <category>Facies</category>
      <category>Geochemistry</category>
      <category>Petrography</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Sedimentary depositional environment, Facies, Geochemistry, Petrography&#10;Venue: Scientific Reports&#10;Year: 2023&#10;Citations: 6</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of kaolinite and iron oxide cements on resistivity and quality of low resistivity pay sandstones</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2023.106568</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4388205616</guid>
      <dc:creator>Anas Muhammad Salisu, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abdulwahab Muhammad Bello, Abdulkarim Al-Hussaini, Abdulrauf R. Adebayo, Abduljamiu O. Amao, Khalid Al–Ramadan</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Electrical resistivity and conductivity</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Kaolinite</category>
      <category>Mineralogy</category>
      <category>Geochemistry</category>
      <description>Topics: Electrical resistivity and conductivity, Geology, Kaolinite, Mineralogy, Geochemistry&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2023&#10;Citations: 19</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decision Tree Ensembles for Automatic Identification of Lithology</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.2118/214460-ms</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4317376201</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mahmoud Desouky, Abdullah Alqubalee, Ahmed Gowida</dc:creator>
      <category>Random forest</category>
      <category>Computer science</category>
      <category>Decision tree</category>
      <category>Identification (biology)</category>
      <category>Hyperparameter</category>
      <description>Abstract: Abstract Lithology types identification is one of the processes geoscientists rely on to understand the subsurface formations and better evaluate the quality of reservoirs and aquifers. However, direct lithological identification processes usually require more effort and time. Therefore, researchers developed several machine learning models based on well-logging data to avoid challenges associated with direct lithological identification and increase identification accuracy. Nevertheless, high uncertainty and low accuracy are commonly encountered issues due to the heterogeneous nature of lithology types. This work aims to employ decision tree ensemble techniques to predict the lithologies more accurately in time saving and cost-efficient manner, accounting for the uncertainty. This study investigated the real-world well logs dataset from the public Athabasca Oil Sands Database to identify and extract the relevant features. Then, we conducted a thorough training using grid search to optimize the hyperparameters of the ensemble decision tree models. This paper evaluated two ensemble techniques: random forest (RF) and extreme gradient boosting (XGB). We picked metrics such as accuracy, precision, and recall to assess the developed models&apos; performance using 5-fold cross-validation. Finally, we performed a chi-squared test to test our hypothesis of the identical performance of the developed models. The XGB and RF models have 94% and 93% accuracy, respectively. Also, the extreme gra…&#10;Topics: Random forest, Computer science, Decision tree, Identification (biology), Hyperparameter&#10;Year: 2023&#10;Citations: 5</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controls on Mechanical Properties of Carbonate Mudstone: Insights from Non-Destructive Techniques and Geochemical Data</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4535426</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4385654401</guid>
      <dc:creator>Baqer Albensaad, Septriandi A. Chan, John Humphrey, Abdullah Alqubalee, Ammar El‐Husseiny, Yaser Alzayer</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>SSRN Electronic Journal</dc:publisher>
      <category>Carbonate</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Geochemistry</category>
      <category>Carbonate rock</category>
      <category>Mineralogy</category>
      <description>Topics: Carbonate, Geology, Geochemistry, Carbonate rock, Mineralogy&#10;Venue: SSRN Electronic Journal&#10;Year: 2023&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of grain-coating illite in preventing quartz cementation: Example from permo-carboniferous sandstone, Central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2022.106073</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4313367735</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdulwahab Muhammad Bello, Khalid Al–Ramadan, Lamidi Babalola, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abduljamiu O. Amao</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Illite</category>
      <category>Cementation (geology)</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Quartz</category>
      <category>Chlorite</category>
      <description>Topics: Illite, Cementation (geology), Geology, Quartz, Chlorite&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 21</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable carbon and oxygen isotope records in a Middle Jurassic carbonate sequence: implications for paleoenvironment, and sea-level fluctuation, central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00531-022-02261-7</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4309553920</guid>
      <dc:creator>Lamidi Babalola, Abdullah Alqubalee, Michael A. Kaminski, Osman Abdullatif, Mohamed O. Abouelresh</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>International Journal of Earth Sciences</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <category>δ18O</category>
      <category>Carbonate</category>
      <category>Meteoric water</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Diagenesis, δ18O, Carbonate, Meteoric water&#10;Venue: International Journal of Earth Sciences&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 5</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First record of shark microremains from the Lower Khartam Member, Khuff Formation: an Upper Permian origin of the genus Lissodus, or a new placement of the Permo/Triassic boundary in Saudi Arabia?</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.29041/strat.19.3.02</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4388593599</guid>
      <dc:creator>Jarrah Babiker, Michael A. Kaminski, John Humphrey, Khalid Al–Ramadan, Jonathan L. Payne, Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Stratigraphy</dc:publisher>
      <category>Permian</category>
      <category>Paleontology</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Genus</category>
      <category>Cretaceous</category>
      <description>Abstract: Shark fossil microremains belonging to the genus Lissodus are recovered for the first time from the Lower Khartam Member of the Khuff Formation in central Saudi Arabia. Previously published research assigned the Lower Khartam Member to the Upper Permian, implying that this is the oldest known record of the genus Lissodus. On the other hand, the stratigraphic occurrence of the recovered Lissodus lies slightly below the previously defined Permian/Triassic boundary in Saudi Arabia. Because Lissodus specimens are common from the Lower Triassic to the Upper Cretaceous, they may provide paleontological evidence for a revised placement of the Permian/Triassic boundary in Saudi Arabia. The Permian/Triassic boundary has been formerly placed at the contact between the Lower and Upper Khartam members of the Khuff Formation in central Saudi Arabia. Earlier studies relied on sequence stratigraphy and geochemistry as tools for identifying the Permian/Triassic boundary. This resulted in placing the boundary at different stratigraphic levels, reflecting the ongoing uncertainty about its actual position. In this study, two scenarios are discussed arguing either for a revised placement of the Permian/Triassic boundary, or a possible Late Permian origin for the genus Lissodus on the Gondwanan continent.&#10;Topics: Permian, Paleontology, Geology, Genus, Cretaceous&#10;Venue: Stratigraphy&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct Petroacoustic Signature of Burrow-Related Carbonate Reservoirs: Outcrop Analog Study, Hanifa Formation, Central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11053-022-10097-w</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4283757143</guid>
      <dc:creator>Ammar El‐Husseiny, Hassan A. Eltom, Abdullah Alqubalee, Ammar Abdlmutalib, Hani Al-Mukainah, Rika N. Syahputra</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Natural Resources Research</dc:publisher>
      <category>Petrophysics</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Carbonate</category>
      <category>Burrow</category>
      <category>Outcrop</category>
      <description>Topics: Petrophysics, Geology, Carbonate, Burrow, Outcrop&#10;Venue: Natural Resources Research&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 10</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pore Volume Characteristics of Clay-Rich Shale: Critical Insight into the Role of Clay Types, Aluminum and Silicon Concentration</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13369-022-06720-w</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4223892951</guid>
      <dc:creator>Clement Afagwu, Mohamed Mahmoud, Saad Alafnan, Abdullah Alqubalee, Ammar El‐Husseiny, Shirish Patil</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering</dc:publisher>
      <category>Oil shale</category>
      <category>Silicon</category>
      <category>Clay minerals</category>
      <category>Materials science</category>
      <category>Aluminium</category>
      <description>Topics: Oil shale, Silicon, Clay minerals, Materials science, Aluminium&#10;Venue: Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 9</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial patterns variations of a burrowed carbonate stratum (ramp carbonates), Upper Jurassic Hanifa Formation, central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sedgeo.2022.106146</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4223471131</guid>
      <dc:creator>M. Rika Nanda Syahputra, Hassan A. Eltom, Ammar El‐Husseiny, Michael A. Kaminski, Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Sedimentary Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Stratum</category>
      <category>Sedimentary depositional environment</category>
      <category>Trace fossil</category>
      <category>Wackestone</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Stratum, Sedimentary depositional environment, Trace fossil, Wackestone&#10;Venue: Sedimentary Geology&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 6</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The negative impact of Ophiomorpha on reservoir quality of channelized deposits in mixed carbonate siliciclastic setting: The case study of the Dam Formation, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2022.105666</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4220873824</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, Jaber Muharrag, Anas Muhammad Salisu, Hassan A. Eltom</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Siliciclastic</category>
      <category>Petrophysics</category>
      <category>Petrography</category>
      <category>Sedimentary rock</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Siliciclastic, Petrophysics, Petrography, Sedimentary rock&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 13</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fish fossil remains from the Khartam Member, Khuff Formation in Central Saudi Arabia: Implications for placement of the Permo/Triassic Boundary</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-egu22-9154</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4221087233</guid>
      <dc:creator>Jarrah Babiker, John Humphrey, Khalid Al–Ramadan, Jonathan L. Payne, Michael A. Kaminski, Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <category>Actinopterygii</category>
      <category>Paleontology</category>
      <category>Permian</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Fish &lt;Actinopterygii&gt;</category>
      <description>Abstract: &amp;amp;lt;p&amp;amp;gt;Recognition of the Permian/Triassic boundary in Saudi Arabia by previous researchers using a variety of methods has resulted in placement of the boundary at different stratigraphic levels. In this study, we discovered two lithological horizons containing fossil fish teeth (sharks and &amp;amp;lt;em&amp;amp;gt;Actinopterygii&amp;amp;lt;/em&amp;amp;gt;) in different stratigraphic positions within the Khartam Member of the Khuff Formation. Thin-section petrography initially revealed the fossil fish teeth, while XRF, XRD, SEM, and QEMSCAN techniques were used to confirm the presence of biogenic apatite. Fish teeth collected from the two stratigraphic levels in the Khartam Member show distinct and different morphological features. The fossil assemblage recovered from the lower unit belongs to the classes&amp;amp;lt;em&amp;amp;gt; Euselachii&amp;amp;amp;#160;&amp;amp;lt;/em&amp;amp;gt;and &amp;amp;lt;em&amp;amp;gt;Actinopterygii&amp;amp;lt;/em&amp;amp;gt;, while fish teeth from the upper unit belong to the shark genus &amp;amp;lt;em&amp;amp;gt;Lissodus&amp;amp;lt;/em&amp;amp;gt;. &amp;amp;amp;#160;The stratigraphic position of the recovered &amp;amp;lt;em&amp;amp;gt;Lissodus&amp;amp;lt;/em&amp;amp;gt; microfossils supports the previous placement of the Permo/Triassic boundary by Vaslet et al. (2005) and Crasquin-Soleau et al. (2006), who placed the boundary exactly at the stratigraphic boundary between the Lower and Upper Khartam Members. The results of this study do not corroborate the boundary placement by Eltom et al. (2016), who placed the Permo/T…&#10;Topics: Actinopterygii, Paleontology, Permian, Geology, Fish &lt;Actinopterygii&gt;&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QUANTITATIVE VARIABILITY OF BURROW PERCENTAGE ESTIMATED FROM 2D VIEWS: EXAMPLE FROM &lt;i&gt;THALASSINOIDES&lt;/i&gt;-BEARING STRATA, CENTRAL SAUDI ARABIA</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.2110/palo.2021.012</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4213326878</guid>
      <dc:creator>Hassan A. Eltom, Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Palaios</dc:publisher>
      <category>Burrow</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Range (aeronautics)</category>
      <category>Paleontology</category>
      <category>Materials science</category>
      <description>Abstract: ABSTRACT This study examines computed tomography (CT) scans of a 15.24-cm diameter and 17.1-cm length core cut from Thalassinoides-bearing strata (Hanifa Formation, central Saudi Arabia) to explore the quantitative variability in burrow percentage when estimated using 2D views. A cropped quadrangular prism of this core allowed 202 2D slices in two vertical orientations and 165 horizontal 2D slices. Thalassinoides volume represents 20.0% (burrow percentage) of the total volume within this cropped quadrangular prism. The estimated burrow percentage by the 2D vertical slices varies from 11.8% to 30.3% with a mean value of 19.9% ± 3.3% and 19.6% ± 3.9%, and coefficients of variation of 17% and 20%, for the two vertical orientations. A wider range and slightly more variability are found when estimated burrow percentage using the horizontal slices (burrow percentage range from 6.1% to 33.1% with a mean value of 19.8% ± 6.5% and coefficient of variation of 33.1%). However, analysis of variance results indicated no statistically significant difference between the distribution of the burrow percentage among vertical and horizontal slices. A test of how randomly selected slices of the CT scan would represent the burrow percentage indicated that even five randomly selected slices could retain a mean comparable to the actual burrow percentage of the CT scan. Based on these results, we suggested a statistical way to quantify the uncertainty associated with estimating the burrow percentage…&#10;Topics: Burrow, Geology, Range (aeronautics), Paleontology, Materials science&#10;Venue: Palaios&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 9</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Negative Impact of Ophiomorpha on Reservoir Quality of Tidal Channel Deposits: The Case Study of the Dam Formation, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4002127</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4205343768</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, JABER MUHARRAG, ANAS MUHAMMAD SALISU, Hassan A. Eltom</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>SSRN Electronic Journal</dc:publisher>
      <category>Channel (broadcasting)</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Quality (philosophy)</category>
      <category>Water resource management</category>
      <category>Hydrology (agriculture)</category>
      <description>Topics: Channel (broadcasting), Geology, Quality (philosophy), Water resource management, Hydrology (agriculture)&#10;Venue: SSRN Electronic Journal&#10;Year: 2022&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geochemistry and organofacies characteristics of organic-rich chalky marl deposits, northern Jordan: Insights into Type II-S source rock</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2021.105040</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W4200149467</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Hail Hakimi, Abbas F. Gharib, Mohammad Alqudah, Adeeb Ahmed, Baleid Ali Hatem, Khairul Azlan Mustapha, Nor Syazwani Zainal Abidin, Aref Lashin, Nura Abdulmumini Yelwa, Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Journal of Asian Earth Sciences</dc:publisher>
      <category>Kerogen</category>
      <category>Maceral</category>
      <category>Marl</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Source rock</category>
      <description>Topics: Kerogen, Maceral, Marl, Geology, Source rock&#10;Venue: Journal of Asian Earth Sciences&#10;Year: 2021&#10;Citations: 5</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the two-dimensional quantification of bioturbation intensity through computer modeling and statistical analysis</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00531-021-02102-z</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3195908734</guid>
      <dc:creator>Hassan A. Eltom, Abdullah Alqubalee, Lamidi Babalola</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>International Journal of Earth Sciences</dc:publisher>
      <category>Bioturbation</category>
      <category>Sedimentology</category>
      <category>Structural geology</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Mineral resource classification</category>
      <description>Topics: Bioturbation, Sedimentology, Structural geology, Geology, Mineral resource classification&#10;Venue: International Journal of Earth Sciences&#10;Year: 2021&#10;Citations: 12</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geochemical Characterization of Subsurface Upper Ordovician Glaciogenic Deposits: Implications for Provenance, Tectonic Setting, and Depositional Environments</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13369-021-06066-9</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3195332584</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, Lamidi Babalola, Osman Abdullatif, Hassan A. Eltom</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering</dc:publisher>
      <category>Ordovician</category>
      <category>Provenance</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Sedimentary depositional environment</category>
      <category>Tectonics</category>
      <description>Topics: Ordovician, Provenance, Geology, Sedimentary depositional environment, Tectonics&#10;Venue: Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering&#10;Year: 2021&#10;Citations: 4</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An experimental study on the effect of magnetic field strength and internal gradient on NMR-Derived petrophysical properties of sandstones</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.petrol.2021.108811</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3152701421</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mahmoud Elsayed, Ammar El‐Husseiny, Ibrahim Kadafur, Mohamed Mahmoud, Murtada Saleh Aljawad, Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Journal of Petroleum Science and Engineering</dc:publisher>
      <category>Petrophysics</category>
      <category>Paramagnetism</category>
      <category>Permeability (electromagnetism)</category>
      <category>Porosity</category>
      <category>Magnetization</category>
      <description>Topics: Petrophysics, Paramagnetism, Permeability (electromagnetism), Porosity, Magnetization&#10;Venue: Journal of Petroleum Science and Engineering&#10;Year: 2021&#10;Citations: 25</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of lithofacies on pore system evolution of storm-wave silt-rich fine-grained sediments. Early Silurian Qusaiba Member (Qaliba Formation), NW Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2021.105048</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3141818123</guid>
      <dc:creator>Ammar Abdlmutalib, Osman Abdullatif, Abdullah Alqubalee, Luis A. González, John Humphrey</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Facies</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <category>Petrophysics</category>
      <category>Mineralogy</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Facies, Diagenesis, Petrophysics, Mineralogy&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2021&#10;Citations: 9</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the permeability of burrow-related gas reservoirs through integrated laboratory techniques</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jngse.2021.103917</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3139415666</guid>
      <dc:creator>Hassan A. Eltom, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abdullah S. Sultan, Assad Barri, Khalid Abdelbasit</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Journal of Natural Gas Science and Engineering</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Permeability (electromagnetism)</category>
      <category>Petrography</category>
      <category>Porosity</category>
      <category>Burrow</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Permeability (electromagnetism), Petrography, Porosity, Burrow&#10;Venue: Journal of Natural Gas Science and Engineering&#10;Year: 2021&#10;Citations: 19</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential overlooked bioturbated reservoir zones in the shallow marine strata of the Hanifa Formation in central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2020.104798</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3102597749</guid>
      <dc:creator>Hassan A. Eltom, Abdullah Alqubalee, Mohamed A. Yassin</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Bioturbation</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Petrophysics</category>
      <category>Ichnology</category>
      <category>Ichnofacies</category>
      <description>Topics: Bioturbation, Geology, Petrophysics, Ichnology, Ichnofacies&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2020&#10;Citations: 30</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for the development of a superpermeability flow zone by bioturbation in shallow marine strata, upper Jubaila Formation, central Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2020.104512</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3035028305</guid>
      <dc:creator>Hassan A. Eltom, Luis A. González, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abduljamiu O. Amao, Moaz Salih</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Marine and Petroleum Geology</dc:publisher>
      <category>Burrow</category>
      <category>Bioturbation</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Siliciclastic</category>
      <category>Carbonate</category>
      <description>Topics: Burrow, Bioturbation, Geology, Siliciclastic, Carbonate&#10;Venue: Marine and Petroleum Geology&#10;Year: 2020&#10;Citations: 30</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Clay Content on the Spin–Spin NMR Relaxation Time Measured in Porous Media</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.9b04228</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3012467253</guid>
      <dc:creator>Mahmoud Elsayed, Guenther Glatz, Ammar El‐Husseiny, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abdulrauf R. Adebayo, Karem Al-Garadi, Mohamed Mahmoud</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>ACS Omega</dc:publisher>
      <category>Clay minerals</category>
      <category>Relaxation (psychology)</category>
      <category>Mineralogy</category>
      <category>Chemistry</category>
      <category>Porosity</category>
      <description>Abstract: Clays, hydrous aluminous phyllosilicates, have a significant impact on the interpretation of physical measurements and properties of porous media. In particular, the presence of paramagnetic and/or ferromagnetic ions like iron, nickel, and magnesium in clays can complicate the analysis of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) data for porous media characterization. This is due to the internal magnetic field gradient induced by the clay minerals. In this study, we aim to investigate the impact of clay content on spin-spin relaxation time (&lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), which is strongly influenced by the pore surface chemistry. Seven rock core plugs, characterized with variable clay content, were used for this purpose. The clay mineralogy and volume were determined by means of quantitative evaluation of minerals by scanning electron microscopy (QEMSCAN). The &lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; relaxation time was measured using a Carr-Purcell-Meiboom-Gill (CPMG) sequence with variable echo spacing (&lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;E&lt;/sub&gt;). The maximum percentage difference in dominant &lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; values (MRD&lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) between shortest and longest echo spacing was subsequently correlated with clay content obtained from QEMSCAN. Our results show that the reduction in &lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; distribution with increasing echo time &lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;E&lt;/sub&gt; is more significant in samples characterized by higher clay contents. The MRD&lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt; &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; was found to be strongly correlated with clay content. …&#10;Topics: Clay minerals, Relaxation (psychology), Mineralogy, Chemistry, Porosity&#10;Venue: ACS Omega&#10;Year: 2020&#10;Citations: 33</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insight into the Pore Characteristics of a Saudi Arabian Tight Gas Sand Reservoir</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.3390/en12224302</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W2988910414</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdulrauf R. Adebayo, Lamidi Babalola, Syed Rizwanullah Hussaini, Abdullah Alqubalee, Rahul S. Babu</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Energies</dc:publisher>
      <category>Porosity</category>
      <category>Petrophysics</category>
      <category>Petrography</category>
      <category>Mineralogy</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <description>Abstract: The petrophysical characterization of tight gas sands can be affected by clay minerals, gas adsorption, microfractures, and the presence of high-density minerals. In this study, we conducted various petrophysical, petrographic, and high-resolution image analyses on Saudi Arabian tight sand in order to understand how a complex pore system responds to measurement tools. About 140 plug samples extracted from six wells were subjected to routine core analyses including cleaning, drying, and porosity–permeability measurements. The porosity–permeability data was used to identify hydraulic flow units (HFU). In order to probe the factors contributing to the heterogeneity of this tight sand, 12 subsamples representing the different HFUs were selected for petrographic study and high-resolution image analysis using SEM, quantitative evaluation of minerals by scanning electron microscope (QEMSCAN), and micro-computed tomography (µCT). Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and electrical resistivity measurements were also conducted on 56 subsamples representing various lithofacies. NMR porosity showed good agreement with other porosity measurements. The agreement was remarkable in specific lithofacies with porosity ranging from 0.1% to 7%. Above this range, significant scatters were seen between the porosity methods. QEMSCAN results revealed that samples with &amp;lt;7% porosity contain a higher proportion of clay than those with porosity &amp;gt;7%, which are either microfractured or contain partially…&#10;Topics: Porosity, Petrophysics, Petrography, Mineralogy, Geology&#10;Venue: Energies&#10;Year: 2019&#10;Citations: 23</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characteristics of Paleozoic tight gas sandstone reservoir: integration of lithofacies, paleoenvironments, and spectral gamma-ray analyses, Rub’ al Khali Basin, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12517-019-4467-0</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W2945148837</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, Osman Abdullatif, Lamidi Babalola, Mohammad Makkawi</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Arabian Journal of Geosciences</dc:publisher>
      <category>Facies</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Outwash plain</category>
      <category>Fluvial</category>
      <category>Arenite</category>
      <description>Topics: Facies, Geology, Outwash plain, Fluvial, Arenite&#10;Venue: Arabian Journal of Geosciences&#10;Year: 2019&#10;Citations: 17</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factors Controlling Reservoir Quality of a Paleozoic Tight Sandstone, Rub’ al Khali Basin, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13369-019-03885-9</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W2944809997</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, Lamidi Babalola, Osman Abdullatif, Mohammad Makkawi</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Authigenic</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <category>Compaction</category>
      <category>Petrography</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Authigenic, Diagenesis, Compaction, Petrography&#10;Venue: Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering&#10;Year: 2019&#10;Citations: 17</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STABLE ISOTOPE CHEMOSTRATIGRAPHY OF A BIOTURBATED MIDDLE JURASSIC CARBONATE SEQUENCE, CENTRAL SAUDI ARABIA: PALEOTEMPERATURE RECONSTRUCTION, DEPOSITION ENVIRONMENT AND DIAGENETIC INTERPRETATIONS</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.1130/abs/2019am-341003</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W2965273680</guid>
      <dc:creator>Lamidi Babalola, Aviandy W. Ismanto, Aviandy W. Ismanto, Abdullah Alqubalee, Abdullah Alqubalee, Mohamed O. Abouelresh, Mohamed O. Abouelresh, Michael A. Kaminski, Michael A. Kaminski, Osman Abdullatif, Osman Abdullatif</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Abstracts with programs - Geological Society of America</dc:publisher>
      <category>Chemostratigraphy</category>
      <category>Diagenesis</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Sequence (biology)</category>
      <category>Carbonate</category>
      <description>Topics: Chemostratigraphy, Diagenesis, Geology, Sequence (biology), Carbonate&#10;Venue: Abstracts with programs - Geological Society of America&#10;Year: 2019&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sedimentological Controls on Reservoir Properties of a Paleozoic Tight Sandstone Reservoir, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.3997/2214-4609.201900217</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W2928602162</guid>
      <dc:creator>Osman Abdullatif, Abdullah Alqubalee, Lamidi Babalola, Mohammad Makkawi</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Proceedings</dc:publisher>
      <category>Paleozoic</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Petroleum reservoir</category>
      <category>Petrology</category>
      <category>Petroleum engineering</category>
      <description>Abstract: Preview this conference paper: Sedimentological Controls on Reservoir Properties of a Paleozoic Tight Sandstone Reservoir, Saudi Arabia, Page 1 of 1 &lt; Previous page | Next page &gt; /docserver/preview/fulltext/2214-4609/2018/APL12-1.gif&#10;Topics: Paleozoic, Geology, Petroleum reservoir, Petrology, Petroleum engineering&#10;Venue: Proceedings&#10;Year: 2018&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Scale Reservoir Characterization of Tight Gas Sand: A Case Study from the Paleozoic Glaciogenic Sarah Formation, Rub’ Al-Khali Basin, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.3997/2214-4609.201702466</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W2766468506</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Proceedings</dc:publisher>
      <category>Paleozoic</category>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Structural basin</category>
      <category>Tight gas</category>
      <category>Ordovician</category>
      <description>Abstract: Summary This study integrates core description, thin section, X-ray diffraction, Scanning Electron Microscopy, porosity and permeability measurements to characterized the Late Ordovician Sarah Formation in Rub’ Al-Khali Basin, Saudi Arabia. Core samples retrieved from six exploratory wells drilled in this basin were used for this study. The Formation is one of the Palaeozoic siliciclastic sequences targeted for unconventional tight gas in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. However, the heterogeneity within the Formation’s lithofacies, depositional environments and deep burial were revealed as major challenges for gas exploration and development activities, particularly, in the studied basin.&#10;Topics: Paleozoic, Geology, Structural basin, Tight gas, Ordovician&#10;Venue: Proceedings&#10;Year: 2017&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reservoir Characterization of Tight Gas Sand - Integration of lithofacies and Petrophysical properties, Subsurface, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://doi.org/10.3997/2214-4609.201701379</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W2618368271</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, Osman Abdullatif, Lamidi Babalola, Mohammad Makkawi</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>Proceedings</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Petrophysics</category>
      <category>Sedimentary depositional environment</category>
      <category>Permeability (electromagnetism)</category>
      <category>Cementation (geology)</category>
      <description>Abstract: Summary The lithofacies heterogeneity, paleoenvironments, and complex paleogeography pose challenges to exploration and development of tight gas sand reservoirs in Saudi Arabia. This study aims to investigate the heterogeneity of the lithofacies and depositional environment of Sarah Formation and to evaluate their reservoir quality. Four lithofacies associations including bioturbated massive sandstone, grayish massive sandstone, diamictites, and partially deformed sandstone were identified and interpreted as nearshore, glaciolacustrine delta, subglacial tillite, and glaciofluvial outwash environments, respectively. The correlation and comparison between the lithofacies and the petrophysical data revealed that the glaciofluvial and the nearshore lithofacies at the western and the eastern margins of the basin have better reservoir characteristics than the glaciolacustrine delta and subglacial lithofacies located close to the basin center. The heterogeneity in permeability data within all the lithofacies is higher than that of porosity data. Both porosity and permeability are diminished by grains compaction, cementation and matrix content. Conversely, the reservoir proprieties are enhanced by natural fractures and feldspar dissolution producing sweet spots intervals. The evaluation of the Sarah Reservoir relies on the understanding of its lithofacies associations and its reservoir characteristics. This study provides leads for solving some of the challenges related to tight gas …&#10;Topics: Geology, Petrophysics, Sedimentary depositional environment, Permeability (electromagnetism), Cementation (geology)&#10;Venue: Proceedings&#10;Year: 2017&#10;Citations: 0</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Spectral Gamma Ray for Lithofacies and Paleo-environmental Interpretation: A Case Study from the Late Ordovician Glaciogenic Deposits, Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://openalex.org/W3128658973</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://openalex.org/W3128658973</guid>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Alqubalee, Osman Abdullatif, Lamidi Babalola</dc:creator>
      <dc:publisher>EGU General Assembly Conference Abstracts</dc:publisher>
      <category>Geology</category>
      <category>Ordovician</category>
      <category>Interpretation (philosophy)</category>
      <category>Paleontology</category>
      <category>Geochemistry</category>
      <description>Topics: Geology, Ordovician, Interpretation (philosophy), Paleontology, Geochemistry&#10;Venue: EGU General Assembly Conference Abstracts&#10;Year: 2017&#10;Citations: 1</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>